Donald M. Hunten Papers 1925-2011 (bulk 1946-2010)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Donald M. Hunten Papers 1925-2010 1946-2011
MS 578
Hunten, Donald M., 1925-2010
Donald M. Hunten Papers. The bulk of this collection consists of 25 notebooks. The majority are related to his career as an astronomical researcher at the University Saskatchewan, Kitt Peak Observatory and the University of Arizona.
9.35 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Donald M. Hunten was born in Montreal on March 1, 1925. He earned a Ph.D. from McGill University, Montreal in 1950. After earning his doctorate he became an assistant professor at the University Saskatchewan. In 1963 Hunten moved to Kitt Peak National Observatory where he joined the newly formed space research group lead by Joe Chamberlain.
In 1974 he moved to the LPL at the University of Arizona where he continued his research of the planetary atmosphere. In 1977 he became a professor of Planetary Sciences and eventually a Regents Professor at LPL.
Dr. Hunten received many honors during his career. In 1982 he was inducted into the National Academy of Science, He was awarded the Kuiper Prize of the Division Planetary Sciences of the American Astronomical Society and in 1998 he was honored with the Adam Fleming Medal of the American Geophysical Union (AGU).
Don Hunten was a major contributor to the unmanned space program. He was very involved in the planning and implementation of many of the NASA planetary missions including Pioneer, Venus, Voyager, Galileo and Cassini.
Dr. Donald M. Hunten retired from the University of Arizona in 2001 but remained scientifically productive through his retirement publishing single author papers in Nature and Icarus up until a couple of years before he died on December 14th, 2010
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series
Series I: Personal files,, 1982, 1995, 2005
Series II: Correspondence files, 1958-2001
Series III: Scholarship files, 1955-2002
Series IV: Grants and proposals, 1955-2002
Series V: Subject files, 1965-2003
Series VI: Photograph files, 1965-2003
Series VII: Dr. Hunten notebooks, 1946-1990
Series VIII: Digital Media: 1946-1990
Scope and Content Note
Donald M. Hunten Papers, 1818-2011 (bulk 1946-2010). The bulk of this collection consists of 25 notebooks. The majority are related to his career as an astronomical researcher at the University Saskatchewan, Kitt Peak Observatory and the University of Arizona. Other items in the collection are correspondence, photographs, computer disks and CD’s.
Gerard Peter Kuiper Papers, MS 480; Michael J. Drake Papers, MS 511; Charles P. Sonett Papers, MS 520; Tom Gehrels, MS 541.
Access Terms
Kitt Peak National Observatory.
University of Arizona-Department of Planetary Science-History.
United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration-History.
Asteroids.
Solar system
Polarization.
Planetary Sciences-History.
Astronomy.
Jupiter
Nuclear magnetic.
Space Imagery.
Aurorae.
Container List
- Personal files, Series I
  - Birthday greetings, 1995; 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congratulation notes /letters on Dr. Hunten’ election to the National Academy of Sciences, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1958-2001.; Series 2
  Includes people and organizations (incoming and outgoing mail)
  - A, 1970-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3:)
  - Academic Press, 1969; 1977,; 1982 (Folder 4:)
  - Akasofu, S.I., 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5:)
  - Atreya, S.K., 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6:)
  - B, 1964-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7:)
  - Barth, Charles A., 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8:)
  - Baum, William, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9:)
  - Belton, Michael J.S., 1966-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bertaux, J.L., 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Best, Gorden T., 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blamont, Jacques E., 1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Briggs, Geoffrey, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Broadfoot, Lyle, 1966-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burns, Joseph, 1982-1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C, 1971-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cameron, A.G.W., 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Carleton, N.P., 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carlson, Herbert C., 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carlson. R.W., circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chamberlain, Joe W., 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chamberlain, Joe W., 1976-1988; 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Chamberlain, Joe W., 1984-1985; 1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chandraiah, G., 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chapman, Clark R., 1977; 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cole, K.D., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Coughlin, Bridget, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Currie, Balfour, 1964-1967; 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - D, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dachs, J., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - de Imke, Pater, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dickinson, Robert, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Donahue, Thomas M., 1966-1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dressler, Alex, 1964-1990 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - DeMore, William B., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - E, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - E, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Elphinstone, Rob, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Eshleman, Von R., 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - F, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - F, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Fastie, William G., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Fink, Uwe, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fjeldbo, Gunnar, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fite, Wade, 1976-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fox, Jane Lee, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Frank, Lou, 1988-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - G, 1978; 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gadsden, Michael, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chandraiah, G., 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gehrels, Tom, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gerard, J.C., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Godson, W.L., 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Goody, Richard M., 1967-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gross, Stanley H., 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - H, 1967-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hansen, Jim, 1968-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hartle, Richard E., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hapke, Bruce, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hodges, Richard, Jr., 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hunaerts, J., 1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Huntress, Wesley t. Jr., circa 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - IP, W.-H., 1982-1983; 1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - J, 1977; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Johnson, Terrence V., 1974-1980; 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jones, Alister V., 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Judge, Darrel L., 1969-1974; 1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - K, 1979; 1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Killen, Rosemary M., 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - L, Personal files; 1968; 1946-1990.; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    This series is arranged by year. There are 24 notebooks of class or work related materials.
    - Nuclear moments. Book II, June 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - P51 Lab., L. Ann Rubenstien, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chemistry 452a, Research; April 1952-April 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Electronics 1; Physics 255, Chemistry and Physics, 1946 (Box 1, Foler 4)
    - Physics 459-365, 1946; April 1953-June 1954 (Box 1, Foler 5)
    - Book III, 1953 (Box 1, Foler 6)
    - Untitled, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - L.B.S., G. Shepherd, 1954 (Box 1, Foler 8)
    - Rotational Temps, University of Saskatchewan, 1954 (Box 1, Foler 9)
    - Electronic computation, 1957 (Box 1, Foler 10)
    - Electronics II, 1957 (Box 1, Foler 11)
    - Aurorae Research VI, June 1954-July 1955 (Box 1, Foler 12)
    - Aurorae Research VII, July 1955-June 1957 (Box 1, Foler 13)
    - Aurorae Research VIII, 1957-September 1958 (Box 1, Foler 14)
    - Aurorae Research IX, September 1958-Febuary 1960 (Box 1, Foler 15)
    - Aurorae Research X, February 1960-March 1964 (Box 1, Foler 16)
    - General Research XI, April 1964 (Box 1, Foler 17)
    - Complex and SSB, September 1976-May 1977; April 1964 (Box 1, Foler 18)
    - NASA, 1976-July 1977 (Box 1, Foler 19)
    - SSB, SAC, SSEC, July 77; November 1977-April 1984, (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - SSB, SAC, SSEC, July 77; May 1984, (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Sodium records wedge photo meters, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Light sources, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Computations, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Other materials. Arranged alphabetically, 1981-1990; Series II
    - Nuclear magnetic moment of Scandium of mass, Super – regenerative proton resonance magnetometer; undated; 2 manuscripts by Dr. Donald Hunten; (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - undated (Box 1, Folder 27, Photographs,)
  - Digital Media:, 1984-1987, 2000, 2002; Series III
    - 3.5 Disks, Subseries 1
      - Ottawa radio flux including some executables for reading, plotting 3.5 disk, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Programs for digital signal processing and pkzip, pkuzip from Richard K, 3.5 disk, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Zurich Sunspot number 1989. See sunspot.doc. Includes some executables for plotting, etc., undated (Box 2, Box 3)
      - Job 13 disk 11, September 9-28, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Floppy disks, Subseries 2
      - CTM-05, UCCTM-05 UTILITY SOFWARE (1 OF 2) floppy disk, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - CTM-05, UCCTM-05 UTILITY SOFWARE (2 OF 2) floppy disk, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - CD’s, undated; Subseries 3
      - Comet D/Shoemaker-Levy 9 Collision with Jupiter; selected spacecraft and earth-based data. 6 CD’s (Box 2, Folder 7)